Continuity announcer: The Food Chain is a BBC World Service podcast series
which focuses on the business, science, and cultural significance of food in our lives.
This episode, Love you, hate your food,
focuses on two couples with very different tastes in food,
and the effect it has had on their lives and relationships.
Presenter: Meals were a battlefield for Sheryl and Dharmesh.
She grew up on southern American food in Tennessee,
but he preferred the typical Indian cooking in his family.
Rebecca and Saj are a London couple dealing with a major split over food –
she’s a vegan, he eats meat. Both couples talk to Emily Thomas.
Emily: Sheryl and Dharmesh Pabu are in their late forties and live in Atlanta,
Georgia, in the US. His family is originally from Gujarat in western India.
She was raised in Tennessee.
Sheryl: I’m a very Southern girl,
so the kinds of things that I loved to eat were fried chicken,
pot roasts with potatoes, you know, seasoned with salt and pepper, nothing spicy.
I ate a lot of hamburgers and hotdogs, sort of the all-American type of food.
Dharmesh: We were raised vegetarian,
so lots of rice and vegetables and carbs and lots of spices.
Emily: And Sheryl, when did you first realize that you had such different attitudes to food?
Sheryl: It was when his mother first had me over for dinner to their house
and fixed a vegetable biriyani with this yogurt motald sauce that goes on it.
There was no meat and it was very spicy.
Emily: Dharmesh was training to be a dentist whilst Sheryl stayed at home,
so she did all the cooking.
Sheryl: My simple, you know, chicken and potatoes,
basic foods, and – that was interesting,
because he would put masala and anything hot and spicy on top of it that he could find.
I felt a little bit insulted, like, you know,
you can understand cultural differences in your head,
but in your heart it’s, it’s hard to accept.
I felt, like, ‘Wow, he doesn’t like my cooking!’
Emily: And, Dharmesh, what were you thinking at the time?
Were you enjoying this food that Sheryl was making? Be honest.
Dharmesh: Er, it was very bland, honestly.
Emily: But Dharmesh’s mum lived nearby
and she’d regularly turn up at the house with meals.
Dharmesh: She brought food any time she could,
and sometimes it was a bit of a tug of war with Mom and Sheryl
because they’d both have food in front of me
and watch which one I’m gonna eat first, so…
Emily: I mean, that must have been quite difficult for you
because you wouldn’t want to offend either.
Dharmesh: Yes, so I overate a lot.
Emily: Dharmesh, thinking back to those early years of marriage
with your mum bringing all this food around,
what do you think was going on for her?
Why do you think she felt she needed to come over and feed you?
Dharmesh: I think that’s just the way Mom shows her love.
She cooks endless amounts of food for everybody.
Emily: Do you think that your conflicts over food were about the food itself,
or was it about what the food represented?
Sheryl: Oh, definitely about what the food represented, 100 per cent,
because over the years I have grown to love Indian food,
but it definitely was a symbol of, you know,
the relationship that I had maybe with his mother and, sort of,
Indian culture as a whole, because I wasn’t really accepted for so many years.
When we would get together with family – you know, extended family –
for dinners, the women would be in the kitchen cooking
and the men would be sitting, you know, in front of the TV.
And I didn’t want to be in the kitchen in that role
because I didn’t want anyone to pressure me to fix a certain type of food,
because I am a meat and potatoes kind of girl, and that’s OK, too.
When we eat together now, he’ll eat something different,
I’ll eat something different. Or I’ll make a dish –
like, we had Fettuccine Alfredo last night,
and I had mine with some Parmesan cheese and he had his with some masala,
and I just say ‘Whatever’.
Dharmesh: I think we have more of a blended menu now,
just happy to be in a kitchen together,
cooking together and having family time.
Emily: And does your mum, Dharmesh, still bring you food?
Dharmesh: Yes, absolutely.
Emily: How often does she bring you food?
Dharmesh: She’d bring it daily, if I allowed it,
but we set some boundaries and, you know…
maybe a few times a week.